またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
小さい頃から時々変なものを見た
Ever since I was small, I would...
sometimes see strange things.
A kappa?
河童
Water...
水…水…
W-Water...
じゃあな
Later.
Shigure and the Girl
Natsume-kun, don't forget, okay?
夏目君 忘れないでね
Eh?
"Eh?" I'm talking about tonight's test of courage.
え？って 今夜の肝試しよ
あ どうしても行かなくちゃ駄目かな
Do I have to go?
I don't really feel up to it.
あまり気が乗らないっていうか
I asked you to come because we didn't have enough people.
頭数足りないって頼んでるのに
Aren't you being a bit anti-social?
ちょっと付き合い悪くない
それでも何か大事な用事でもあるの
Or is it that you have something more important to do?
That's not it.
そういう訳じゃ
旧校舎来週取り壊すから
The old school building is going to be demolished next week,
so this year's test of courage will be the last one.
肝試しは今年が最後なの
Make sure you come, since we'll be waiting.
必ず来て 待ってるから
During the dark nights of summer, there are more lurking Youkai.
夏の闇夜には潜む妖怪が多くなる
肝試しなんて 平気だろうか
Will I be okay if I do the test of courage?
お 来たな 夏目
You're here, Natsume.
あ それ夏目ん家の猫か
Is that your cat?
あ 何でついてくるんだよ
Why'd you follow me?
Come on, it looks fun.
いいじゃないか 面白そうだし
You need me as a bodyguard for times like this, right?
こういう時こそ用心棒だろう
That may be true, but...
それはそうかもしんないけど
Did that cat just make a strange noise?
なんか今 その猫から変な声しなかったか
いや き…気のせいだろう
N-No, you're probably just imagining it.
そうか
Oh...
Make sure you don't talk in front of anyone!
ぜーったい皆の前でしゃべるなよ
You're a real handful, you know.
お前は本当に世話がやけるな
What'd you say?
何だと
All right, I got it already.
分かった 分かった
The instructions are to go in pairs,
ルールは二人一組で
write your names on the wall at the end of the second floor hall,
二階の突き当たりの壁に名前を書いて戻ってくること
and then come back.
嚇かし役はいないので
We haven't set up people to scare you, so you can be scared safely.
安心して怖がって来てください
ペアは籤引きで 1番から20番までの番号順で決めます
We'll decide the pairings through a lottery
ranging from one to twenty.
それじゃ 全員引いてください
All right. Everyone draw a lot.
There's a story about this building.
この校舎には逸話があるんだって
In the past, there was a god of fortune who loved humans,
昔 人間が好きな招福の神様がいて
子供に化けては村に遊びに来ていたらしいの
and he would appear as a child to play among the villagers.
However,
ところが
ある強欲な商人がますますの繁栄を願って
there was a greedy merchant who wanted more riches,
and he locked him up in his cellar.
地下牢に閉じ込めてしまったそうなの
商人はその日から招福パワーで大儲け
After that, the merchant would reap huge profits because of the fortune power.
But in the dark cellar, the God of Youth mourned and mourned,
でも若神様は暗い地下で悲しんで悲しんで
人を恨み やがて悪しきもののけとなってしまった
grew to resent people,
and eventually became an evil spectre.
商人の家は潰れてしまい
The merchant's house became bankrupt,
不吉となったその場所にやがてその校舎が建てられた
and eventually this school building was erected on this spot of bad luck.
The God of Youth lamented that he became an abominable Ayakashi,
若神様は忌まわしい妖になってしまったことを嘆いて
and even now he wanders this place, or so they say.
今もこの場所をさまよってるんですって
どうして俺にそんな話をするんだ
Why are you telling me this?
No real reason.
別に
よーし 全員引き終わったな
So everyone drew one?
Then show your lots on the count of three.
それに一斉に籤を出してください
One, two...
せーの
あれ　一枚足りない
Huh? We're missing one lot.
There were twenty numbers, though.
でも20番はちゃんといるぞ
We have one person too many.
一人多いな
落ち着け
Calm down!
参加希望出さずに来てるやつがいるだけだろう
It's probably just someone who came and didn't bother to sign up!
The committee did this on purpose, didn't they?
実行委員わざとだろう
No!
そんなことねーよ
Maybe someone took two.
誰か両手出したんじゃね
Is there something here?
何かいるのか
I'm not sure.
分からんな
先笹田が話していたやつか
Is it the thing Sasada talked about earlier?
さあ いるとすれば
Well, if he's here,
この私に気配を感じさせないことができる程のやつだな
then he must be strong enough that even I can't sense him.
It's getting interesting.
面白くなってきた
先生
Sensei.
It can't be...
まさか 友人帳のせいじゃないだろうな
It can't be the Book of Friends' fault, can it?
We should've been paired up with girls.
俺らも せっかくなら女子と組みたかったよな
Yeah.
It's run-down, but it kind of makes you feel sad that it's going to be demolished.
ぼろぼろだけど
壊されると思うとちょっと寂しいな
Yeah.
なんか全然他のやつと会わないな
We haven't seen anyone else yet.
そういや そうだな
That's true, now that you mention it.
あれ？
どっち行くんだっけ
Which way were we supposed to go, again?
えっと
一人で何やってんだ
What are you doing here alone?
えっと 相方はどうしちゃったのかなーなんて
What about the password?
おい 大丈夫か
Hey, are you okay?
So, you've awakened.
目覚めてしまったか
うん？ その顔どこかで
Where have I seen that face before?
まあ いい
Never mind that.
私を不浄のものとした上
Not only have you defiled me, but now you're stealing my home?
住処まで奪おうとは
People are such selfish beings.
とかく 人というものは身勝手なものよ
夏目君 どうしたの 大丈夫？
Natsume-kun!
What's wrong?
Are you okay?
待て
Wait!
What's wrong?
どうしたの 誰もいないわよ
There's no one there.
Y-Yeah...
あれ 西村君は？
Where's Nishimura-kun?
ね 私と組んでた北本君見なかった
Hey, did you see my partner, Kitamoto-kun?
I took my eyes off of him for a second, and then we got separated.
ちょっと目を離した隙に逸れちゃったみたいで
いいや
No.
先発組も帰ってこないし
The first group still hasn't returned either.
Where is everyone?
皆どうしたんだろう
そうか 皆やつに連れて行かれたんだな
I see.
Everyone was taken away by him.
先誰に声かけてたの
Who were you calling out to earlier?
ね 夏目君って 見えてるんでしょう
Hey, Natsume-kun,
you can see them, can't you?
時々変な行動とるわよね
You do strange things sometimes.
You're startled when there's nothing there,
何もない所でびくっとしたり
and talk when there's no one there.
相手もいないのに何かと話してたり
Hey, what can you see?
ね 何が見えるの
Are they things not of this world?
ひょっとしてこの世のものでないもの
もしそうなら 皆には黙っててあげるから
If that's the case,
I'll keep it a secret from everyone.
私に協力してくれない
Could you help me?
So, what is it? You can see them, can't you?
どうなの 本当は見えるんでしょう
ああ ニャンコ先生
Nyanko-sensei!
うん こいつあやかしものではなかったか
So she wasn't an Ayakashi.
Probably.
多分な
It's no use.
駄目だ
It seems like there's a barrier around the entire school building and we can't get out.
校舎全体に結界が張ってあって
出られないようになっているな
Could you go and see if there's a way out somewhere, sensei?
先生 どっかに出口ないか探してきてくれないか
What?
何 人使いの荒いやつだ
What a slave driver.
W-What's with that look?
な…何だその格好
こっちの方がなにかと都合よかろう
This form will be more convenient.
Something...
なんか ドッチボールみたいなのが飛んできて…
Something like a dodgeball came flying at me...
Who's this?
誰
Ah, well...
いや この人はドッチボール部の人で
S-She's part of the dodgeball club,
and came to get her ball that got away.
飛び込んできたボールを取りに来たらしくって
へえ ドッチボール部なんてあったんだ
So we had a dodgeball club.
All right, I'll go take a look around.
それじゃ 様子を見て来てやる
I'll look for a way out,
脱出までは面倒を見てやるから
so relax.
安心しろ
She seemed pretty conceited.
なんか偉そうなのね
しゅ…主将だからね
Sh-She's the captain, after all.
It's a person! A person!
人だ 人だ
It's a person!
まだ残っていたか
So, people are still around here.
We must report this to Shigure-sama.
時雨様に報告せねば
Hey, you low-level punks!
こら 低級ども
Our eyes met!
や 目があった
逃げて
Run away!
こっちだ　こっちだ
This way, this way!
When I was in middle school,
中学の時 地区のイベントで
there was a district event, so I participated in a test of courage here.
ここの肝試しに参加したの
I cried and ran around the school building,
私 泣いたり校内中を走り回っちゃったりして
and when I got home, I realized I had lost something precious.
家に帰ってから
大事なものをなくしたことに気付いたの
慌てて学校に一人で探しに戻したんだけど
In a panic, I went back to the school to search for it alone.
I was scared and disheartened,
すっごく怖くて心細くて
but I couldn't find it at all.
でも全然見つからなくて
And then...
そんな時
先から何をしている
What have you been doing this entire time?
I-I dropped my charm.
お…お守りを落としちゃって
とっても大事なものなんです
It's very precious to me.
Find it quickly and leave immediately.
さっさと探してとっとと帰れ
その後も暫く諦めずに探し続けたんだけど
And after that,
I didn't give up and continued to look for it for a while,
but I couldn't find it.
全然見つからなかった
And just when I was about to give up...
それで途方にくれていた時に
Hey.
おい
これか
Is this it?
Yes! That's it!
そう これ
よかった 半分諦めてたの
Thank goodness...
I had almost given up.
This is a memento from my mother.
これ お母さんの形見で
でもその棒切れは何
What's that stick, though?
An impure being such as myself cannot touch anything that is pure.
私のように不浄なものは清いものには触れられん
You're done now, aren't you?
もういいだろう さっさと帰れ
Hurry up and leave.
Impure?
不浄？ それって何のこ…と…
What are you talking...
about?
With the way he talked and his presence,
あの言葉遣いとか雰囲気とか
あの人ひょっとしてお化けなんじゃないかって思って
I wondered if he was a ghost.
それで色々調べて あの若神様の逸話を知ったの
So I looked it up and learned the story about the God of Youth.
I also learned that "impure" meant "defiled."
不浄が汚れてるって意味だってことも分かった
それから毎日ここに通ったわ
After that, I would come here every day.
I wanted to thank him, and so called for him to come out.
きちんとお礼が言いたいから出て来てって
And I wanted to say, "You're not impure!"
あなたは不浄じゃないって伝えてかったの
でも 結局姿を見せてくれなくって
But in the end, he never showed himself to me.
That's why, if you can see things like that,
だから夏目君にそういうものが見えるなら
I want you to help me.
手伝って欲しいって思ったの
This place is going to be demolished,
ここも取り壊されるし
so I thought that this was my last chance.
最後のチャンスだと思って
Sorry for saying it like that earlier.
ごめんね 先はあんな言い方しちゃって
It's okay.
いいんだ
You really can't see them, Natsume-kun?
夏目君 本当に見えないの
Yeah.
I see.
そう
No one came back.
誰も戻ってない
Where is everyone?
皆どうしたんだろう
あれ 夏目君
Natsume-kun?
Where are you?
どこ
Nyanko-sensei!
ニャンコ先生
His servants are low-level, but he's a surprisingly big one.
子分どもは下等だが
相手は以外とは大物だぞ
His name seems to be in the Book of Friends as well.
しかも友人帳に名があるらしい
The Ayakashi's name is Shigure.
あのあやかしの名は時雨
Shigure...
時雨
He's a real bother, so let's leave now.
面倒だからさっさと帰るぞ
It's a powerful barrier, but I can manage to break it.
強力な結界だが私なら何とか破れる
Get on.
乗れ
What about everyone?
皆は どうするんだ
Forget them.
放っておけ
You don't like people, right?
お前人は好きではないんだろう
You have nightmares about your childhood, don't you?
子供の頃の夢を見てはうなされているじゃないか
That...
それはそうかもしれないけど
That may be true...
But even so, we can't leave them alone.
でもだからって 放ってはおけない
I want do things that I can do!
俺にやれることはやっておきたいんだ
Natsume-kun!
夏目君 どこ
Where are you?
Natsume-kun!
夏目君 大丈夫
Are you all right?
Y-Yeah.
The underlings are gathering.
下っ端どもが集まってきているな
やつは屋上だ夏目
He's on the roof, Natsume.
Yeah.
The roof?
屋上？ やつって？
Who's "He"?
もしかしてあの人のこと…
Do you mean...
Him?
Where are you going, Sasada?
どこ行くんだ 笹田
To see him!
あの人に会いに
He's on the roof, isn't he?
いるんでしょう 屋上に
Well...
それは…
I want to tell him!
伝いたいの
I want to tell him how precious this charm is,
このお守りがどれだけ私にとって大切だったか
and how happy I was that he found it!
見つけてもらってどれだけ嬉しかったか
Watch out!
危ない
Take Sasada somewhere safe, sensei.
先生 笹田を安全な所に頼む
I'm counting on you!
What are you planning to do?
お前どうする気だ
止めさせる
Make him stop.
I'll return his name and persuade him!
名前を返して説得する
な…夏目君
Na...
Natsume-kun!
Oh? I was wondering where you had gone,
おや ちょこまかとどこへ行ったかと思えば
and now you've come to me?
そちらから来るとは
Please stop this.
こんなこと止めてください
断る
I refuse.
I hate people.
人は嫌いだ
They turned me into this abominable Ayakashi,
私をこんな卑しい妖にして
entered this place as if to make fun of me,
冷やかすようにここへ足を踏み入れ
and even tried to steal my home.
住処さえ奪おうとする
決して返さぬ
I will never return them.
お前達の親が嘆き悲しむ様を見てやりたいわ
I want to see your parents crying and mourning.
There's a girl who wants to see you.
女の子が会いたがっています
The other girl left inside the building.
校内に残ったもう一人の女の子が
どうして会ってやらないんです？
Why won't you see her?
君には分からんよ 夏目殿
You wouldn't understand, Natsume-dono.
You're Reiko's relative, aren't you?
君はレイコの縁者だろう
You could have just used the Book of Friends to make me obey.
友人帳を使って従わせればいいものを
What a kind person.
お人好しだね
Then that makes things easier. I will return your name.
なら話が早い 名を返します
I don't need it!
いらねー
I don't need liberation!
解放などいらぬ
I no longer need that defiled name.
もはや汚れた名など
You should have just burnt it up!
煮るなり焼くなりしてくれればよかったものを
Shigure-sama, I return your name.
時雨様 名を返します
A name that belongs to a kind being who helped support a girl's heart.
一人の女の子の心を支えた優しい者の名前です
Come out! Please!
出て来て お願い
ああ また来た うるさいやつが
That noisy one has come again.
I want to thank you! I just have to!
お礼が言いたいの どうしても
I just wanted to drive her out quickly,
たった一度 さっさと追い出したくて
and so I helped her.
手伝ってやっただけなのに
Day after day,
毎日毎日飽きもせず
and never giving up...
What a bizarre being.
なんとけったいな生き物か
If an impure being such as myself touched her...
不浄の私が触れたらば
Would I really defile her?
やはり汚してしまうだろうか
Please! Just once!
お願い 一度だけでもいいから
ああ そうか
I see, just by meeting her once...
一度会ってしまったら
Please!
お願い
You...
君はもう来なくなる
You won't come again...
Thank you, Natsume.
ありがとう 夏目
I will go.
私は行くよ
駄々をこねるのも疲れた
I'm tired from being unreasonable.
あ 時雨様 笹田は言ってました
Shigure-sama!
Sasada said...
She said that you're not impure!
時雨様は不浄なんかじゃないって
She said you saved her!
救ってもらったんだって
You don't need to believe in a person's words,
人の言葉なんて信じなくてもいいから
but at least believe in Sasada's—
どうか 笹田の言葉だけは…
Natsume-kun!
夏目君
Are you okay?
大丈夫
すまなかった 人の子よ
I am sorry, child.
Only you and Reiko did not fear me for being impure.
私を不浄と恐れなかったのは 君とレイコだけなのだ
Thank you.
ありがとう
Natsume-kun.
夏目君
Sasada.
笹田
Natsume-kun, last night, I...
夏目君 あのう 昨夜 私…
Yeah, what happened?
あ どうしちゃったんだろうな
Everyone was on the roof and sleeping.
皆して屋上で居眠りなんて
Ah, yeah.
そう そうだね
That's right.
Sasada, the truth is that for a moment, I saw Shigure-sama touch you.
笹田 本当は一瞬君に触れる時雨様を見たよ
I saw your hearts trying to connect.
交差しようとする心が見えたよ
I wonder if you felt anything.
君も何かを感じだろうか
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
夕立の雨上がりに
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
Heart-Colored Ticket
The one ticket that Reiko-san left behind.
レイコさんが残した一枚の切符
If you visit the old train station, there is one Youkai there.
古い駅を訪ねると そこに一匹の妖怪がいた
What a slow-looking guy. We should just leave him alone.
鈍そうなやつだな ほっとけばいいんじゃないか
俺 さんと 頼むよ みくりに会いたいんだ
I am Santou.
Please! I want to see Mikuri!